MIKEWEST

Mike West is a web application developer who has professionally programmed for the web since 1998. By working on a wide variety of projects ranging from UI consulting to enterprise-level PHP products, Mike has developed the experience and expertise to deliver quality solutions that work and build value for their users.



Applicable Buzzwords

PHP, JavaScript, AJAX, CSS, HTML, SQL, XML, XSLT, Perl, UI, Ruby on Rails, Object-Oriented

Contact

mike@mikewest.org http://mikewest.org/ +49 (0) 7423 877 2966

Education

In 2003, I graduated from the **University of Texas at Austin** with a degree in Philosophy and minors in Computer Science and German. This liberal-arts background is fairly unusual among programmers; I see it as a distinct advantage. Philosophy, combined with my experience as a debater in high school, provides solid mechanisms for analyzing problems and crafting solutions in a clear and systematic way.

I left Texas in December 2005, moving to Oberndorf, Germany. Currently, I'm working my way through additional language classes at **Stuttgart Universität** to better integrate myself into my new surroundings.

Expertise

I do the vast majority of my programming work in **PHP**: At Dallas Airmotive my team designed and built a large-scale, **object-oriented PHP** system that touched every part of the organization. At RightNow, I customized a PHP CRM for clients' individual needs and integrated it into various backend systems. **Apache** and **MySQL** running on some flavour of **Unix** drove both these systems.

JavaScript is rapidly becoming a critical part of any web application's **UI**. I've published a number of articles regarding its unobtrusive use, and released an easy to integrate, event-driven **AJAX** library under the LGPL.

Elegant JavaScript-based UI improvements are, of course, intertwined with well constructed HTML documents. I generally hand-code sites' **CSS** and **HTML**, adhering to standards as strictly as I reasonably can.

I use **XML** and **XSLT** fairly extensively as a clean mechanism for data transfer between application components, both serverside in PHP and client-side through JavaScript.

Beyond my coding proficiency, I understand SQL and can design and work with complex relational databases. I can communicate intelligently with technical and non-technical audiences. Relatedly, I can write documentation for my team and for the end-user.

Experience

Application Engineer at RightNow Technologies

Mar. 2005 - Jan. 2006

I worked directly with clients to customize RightNow's complete CRM solution to meet their needs and to integrate it into pre-existing backend systems. My role ranged from small tweaks to the software's UI, up to sweeping rewrites that created completely new functionality.

I worked both on- and off-site, serving clients like Motorola, Orbitz, and PricewaterhouseCoopers, and was responsible both for scoping each project and implementing the scoped changes. A variety of languages were used, PHP primarily, with Perl, Python, Ruby, and Bash scripting mixed in to varying extents on a project-by-project basis depending on the clients' needs.

Web Programmer at Dallas Airmotive

Aug. 2003 - Mar. 2005

I helped design and implement Turbine Update: a suite of applications responsible for everything from internal ticket tracking for the IT and maintenance departments to a client-facing ERP system allowing customers to track their engines' repair status. It's a huge, object-oriented PHP system that touches literally every department in the company.

My responsibilities included aspects of the project's entire life-cycle, including gathering initial requirements, documenting specifications, designing database models, building various user interfaces, writing large chunks of the backend, and squashing annoying bugs. I also wrote the end-user documentation.

IT Department at Moreland Properties

Jan. 2001 - Aug. 2003

I was the entire IT department for this 88-agent real estate firm. I developed their website and intranet, administered their network and hardware, provided technical support, and made purchasing recommendations.